טוב, Tov, today's דף daf is... today's מסכת masechet is בבא מציעא,
Bava Metzia, and today's דף daf is בבא מציעא Bava Metzia ב'
עמוד א', bet amud aleph, ב' bet עמוד א', amud aleph, that's
a bad sign already, ב'. bet. Okay, בבא מציעא Bava Metzia means
literally middle gate, because נזיקין Nezikin is broken up into three sections,
thirty פרקים, prakim, by the way, if I hadn't mentioned this already,
there's another מסכת masechet that has thirty פרקים, prakim, כלים Kelim and
טהרות, Toharot, which has
בבא קמא, Bava Kama, בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, בבא בתרא, Bava Batra,
so it just means first section, middle section, final section. And as
opposed to בבא קמא, Bava Kama, which was very nicely, thematically, sort
of, you know, sort of held together, tightly connected, basically it
was all about torts, whether damages, or robbery, or theft, or personal
injury, but it clearly had one big major theme about it, you
know, that was torts. בבא מציעא Bava Metzia and בבא בתרא, Bava
Batra, בבא בתרא Bava Batra is a little more thematically sort of
unified, בבא מציעא Bava Metzia is a little bit all over the
place. You know, the classic picture of בבא קמא Bava Kama is
an ox goring an ox. The classic picture of בבא מציעא, Bava
Metzia, I would say, is one of two, probably, it's two people
holding on to a טלית, talit, which is our first משנה, mishna,
which is like a great image and gets on a discussion of
this contesting of who owns things, how do you sort of try
to adjudicate and to determine who owns it if it's being contested
and no one person has a clear default ownership about it. But
then it gets on and the other thing that a lot of
people know, because they learn this in, you know, it's a classic
פרק perek that's taught in the grade schools, is the second one
is about אלו מציאות, Elu Metziot, and often people confuse בבא מציעא,
Bava Metzia, it sounds like a מציאה. metzia. מציעא Metzia in Aramaic
means middle, but מציאה metzia with an אלף-הא aleph-hey means a found
object. So there's a piece of that which is about lost objects,
but that doesn't stay there, a lot of בבא מציעא Bava Metzia
is about שומרים. shomrim. The third פרק perek is about שומרים, shomrim,
the eighth פרק perek returns to שומרים. shomrim. Right in the middle
we've got two פרקים, prakim, which might be some of the most
hardest פרקים prakim in ש"ס, Shas, so prepare yourself, which is איזהו
נשך Eizehu Neshech and הזהב, HaZahav, right, which is about basically like
ריבית ribbis and monetary, like sort of
the nature of money, and very hard, you know, just technically difficult
issues. And then later on it returns back to שומרים shomrim issues,
and another very relevant issue for today is workers' rights is a
whole section of בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia. So I would not try
to find one big theme that connects all these things together, you
know, it is just the middle ten פרקים prakim of נזיקין, Nezikin,
which comprises, you know, civil law. So a lot of these things.
A reasonable question still is what is the order of the פרקים,
prakim, even if there's a lot of different things, let's discuss them
in some logical, you know, order, and you can try to figure
that out, I certainly don't know it, but that's just a little
bit of a preview of what we're going to be looking at
in בבא מציעא. Bava Metzia. It is a classic Yeshivish מסכת, masechet,
you know, all of the major ראשונים rishonim and so on, and
as we'll see as we get to it, a lot of very,
you know, almost like ש"ס Shas topics, you know, things that relate
broadly to larger types of questions that come up in the גמרא.
Gemara. So let's just jump in now. שניים אוחזים בטלית, Shnayim ochazim
b'talit, two people are holding onto a טלית, talit, a, you know,
a cloak. A טלית talit is not is not meant as a
religious item with a ציצית tzitzis hanging from it. The two people
are grabbing onto a cloak. זה אומר אני מצאתיה וזה אומר אני
מצאתיה. Ze omer ani metzatiha v'ze omer ani metzatiha. I found it,
this one said I found it. There's again the word מציאה, metzia,
so maybe you have two things about מציאה metzia in בבא מציעא,
Bava Metzia, the next פרק perek which is about finding lost objects,
and maybe starting here with lost objects, maybe that's why we're even
talking about it, maybe as a type of a lead in to
the second פרק perek which is about lost objects, but nevertheless this
whole first פרק perek has nothing to do with lost objects. זה
אומר כולו שלי וזה אומר כולו שלי. Ze omer kulo sheli v'ze
omer kulo sheli. This one says it's all mine and this one
says it's all mine. זה ישבע שאין לו פחות מחציו וזה ישבע
שאין לו פחות מחציו ויחלוקו. Ze yishava she'ein lo pachos mechertzi v'ze
yishava she'ein lo pachos mechertzi v'yeichaleku. So how do you determine, how
do you, what do you do with it? It's sort of like
the classic שלמה המלך, Shlomo HaMelech, right? So why don't you say,
okay let's cut it in half, and the other person says no,
no such a wonderful טלית, talit, give it to the other person?
No, anyway, but actually you do cut it in half. It's great.
Okay, but the question is, right, that's all very nice that you
cut it in half and you split it, I mean not literally
take out a scissor, you figure out the way, like one person
buys half of it off of the other person, or you sell
and then you split the money. Okay, but the point is they
both had equal claims, they're both holding on to it, they're both
saying equal things, so there's no way of determining who's more right
than the other person, so that leads to the decision of ויחלוקו.
yeichaleku. We'll see in the גמרא Gemara that sometimes there are other
ways of deciding it, maybe we should just put it all to
escrow, maybe we should let them fight it out. But the most
logical thing here is that they're both holding onto it, so you
split it. The question is why do you take an oath?
And why is the oath this way?
Well right, why is the oath this one says I have no
less than a
half? Why doesn't each one swear that I have all of it?
Because then someone's lying.
Because then you know you are basically forcing somebody to take a
false oath. Why doesn't each one swear that I have half? half
of it.
Why you have to swear I have no less than half?
Why do you think? Jonathan, you're there saying it's all yours. I
ask you, if I asked you what would you say if I
asked you to swear that half of it is yours?
With that language, because it's asking you to say something that is
undermining your own claim. Right, if you want me to ask that
I have no less than a half, that I'll say, but to
say that I have a half sounds like I have only a
half and you're asking me basically to retract my claim. Okay, so
we make it oath that does not per, you know, what's called
suborn per, what's the word? Suborn perjury? Is that the word? Suborn?
No, suborn. Is it?
Suborn, thank you, got a lawyer. Suborn perjury, so we don't suborn
false oaths. We don't force somebody to make a false oath. We
don't force somebody to swear about something that is, you know, not
true to their claim. It's a very art, you know, very well-crafted
way of taking the oath. What's the purpose of the oath? Presumably
the purpose is that we hope that the oath will get somebody
who's lying to admit. Okay, and so if we can't really get
to the truth, there's no witnesses, maybe we can try to force
the truth out, not through a שלמה המלך Shlomo HaMelech device, but
through something that'll more work on a regular basis. You know, get
somebody to swear and maybe somebody will admit. Now that assumes, and
this is going to be a major question in the מסכת, masechet,
but the general assumption is someone might be willing to lie and
to steal, but not willing to take a false oath. So maybe
I see your cloak, I really want it, I grab it and
I say it's mine, and you say it's yours, okay? But the
oath will make me say, no, no, no, have to take an
oath? Forget it, let him keep it. Okay, so I might be
willing to steal, but I won't be willing to take a false
oath.
What if you go all the way, make everybody swear all the
way? What? All the way? Like as it could be more of
a deterrent?
In other cases, you know...
In other cases...
What do you mean? That it's all mine? Because then, because it's
not always true. First of all, it's not always true that people
will... it's not a deterrent. No, we're not using it as a
deterrent. We're using it as you might not know the law,
but we're using it as a way that now you come to
the court and we say you have to swear. It doesn't necessarily
stop me from grabbing. I might not know the law. But once
we get to the court, it might stop me from going through
with it.
Now but someone who has to swear on the whole thing, that's
even more of a lie.
Yeah, but the likelihood that, I don't know, we don't want because
it's also we don't want to deal with the end result that
both people swore that it's both theirs and we know we've caused
somebody to take a false oath. And then everybody questions the judgment
of בית דין. Beis Din. Both people swore it was theirs, so
it's making a declaration
like we don't know what we're doing. So the small gain that
we'd gain from that is not worth the cost.
So, anyway, so that's an important principle and that's a principle called
חשוד אממונא לא חשוד אשבועתא. chashud amamona lo chashud ashvuasa.
Somebody that might be suspect of monetary issues, of theft, you know,
or whatever, is not suspect of swearing falsely. We think that you
might be stealing, but if you're asked to swear, you'll separate. Now,
it's not necessarily that's the only explanation. It could be that if
in your mind you are willing to do an act of גניבה
gneiva or גזילה, gzeila, you'd, that's the type of person you are,
you'll swear falsely. But a lot of times, coming up to ראש
השנה, Rosh Hashana, important principle to know in life, people are really
expert at rationalizing things, okay, to themselves, right? So a lot of
times you might, if I knew I was stealing it from you
and I was willing to steal, I'd swear falsely about it too.
But in my mind, I'm not stealing it from you. In my
mind, like,
I really saw that, I believe I saw that, I convinced myself
I saw that object first. So sure I saw Michael was there,
but I really saw it beforehand. Or sure it's his cloak, but
he owes me money, really it is mine, and I rationalize. So
if I'm rationalizing, but basically I believe myself to be a good
honest guy, the שבועה shvua will
get me to admit. So clearly the assumption here is that in
absence of an opportunity to get other types of evidence, but a
desire to get more down to the truth, we have them make
a שבועה, shvua, and we believe a שבועה shvua will help. It'll
either help because even for a real גנב ganav he won't swear
falsely, or it'll help because it'll stop people's rationalizing, and that's why
a שבועה shvua will help. So that is the ruling here. You
split it after they've made a שבועה. shvua. Now we continue. זה
אומר Ze omer ויחלוקו, ve'yachloku, and then they'll split it. זה אומר
כולו שלי וזה אומר חציו שלי. Ze omer kulo sheli veze omer
chetzi sheli. This one says it's all mine and this one says
half mine.
So by saying it's half mine, what he's basically doing is he's
conceding that half belongs to the other guy, and therefore they're just
contesting the other half. So in that case,
he's going to be not as well off. האומר כולו שלי ישבע
שאין לו בו פחות משלושה חלקים. Ha'omer kulo sheli yishava she'ein lo
bo pachos mishlosha chalakim. The one who says it's all mine swears
he has no less than three quarters, because that's what we're going
to give him in the end. והאומר חציו שלי ישבע שאין לו
בו פחות מרביע. Veha'omer chetzi sheli yishava she'ein lo bo pachos mirvia.
The one who says it's half mine swears he has no less
than a quarter, because that's what he's going to get in the
end. זה נוטל שלושה חלקים וזה נוטל רביע. Ze notel shlosha chalakim
veze notel rivia. This one gets three quarters and this one gets
a quarter. three quarters that one gets a quarter. So you got
the idea? By saying it's half mine, he's basically conceding like he's
saying we both picked it up at the same time, it's half
mine. So he's conceding that half belongs to that other guy. So
the other guy starts with half to his credit. Where now we're
debating the second half. So we're debating the second half, I say
the second half belongs to me, he says it belongs to him,
we're going to split it. So if you split the second half,
one guy winds up with three quarters and one guy winds up
with a quarter. So you split the part of the garment that
they are debating. And then the oath that you take reflects what
you're going to get at the end. And by the way, going
back to Eli's question, you understand that this really makes בית דין
Beis Din look good, right? You swore you have no less than
three quarters, you swore you have no less than quarter, we give
you three quarters, you give a quarter, to everybody it's like, oh,
justice was done, right? That's the oath he took. So not only
is it like in the other case like we've caused a false
oath, you swore and we awarded you what you swore for, right?
It all looks very nice. Justice was served. Okay, so that's what
happens. Now תוספות Tosafot asks the question and תוספות Tosafot says, what
do you think he's confused about?
I mean, the guy says חציו שלי, chetzyo sheli, swear he has
as חציה. chetzyah.
So that's what תוספות Tosafot says. תוספות Tosafot says, well, why don't
if I say it's half mine, why doesn't like why don't I
have like a little bit of a מיגו? migo? I could have
said it's all mine and would have gotten half. If I'm saying
it's half mine, so you should believe me that it's half mine
because and maybe I shouldn't even have to take a שבועה, shvua,
but minimally I should be able to get that half with a
שבועה, shvua, right? Whatever happened to the whole idea of a מיגו?
migo? So תוספות Tosafot discusses that and תוספות's Tosafot answer, what he's,
I mean, I'll give you one of his answers. One of his
answers is that it's considered a מיגו להוציא, migo lehotzi, that it's
not just a מיגו migo that lets me hold onto something that's
mine, it's a מיגו migo that allows me to take something away
from you. Because here's an important principle that I haven't explicitly spelled
out yet, which is everybody knows, or everyone knows, in הלכה halacha
there's a concept of being מוחזק muchzak in something, of having a
default sense of being the owner. That could be mean physically in
possession of it, right? So this thing is under my control, I'm
מוחזק muchzak in it. But it could also mean just like, you
know, it's known to be mine, right? Everybody knows, you know, what
my car is. I'm מוחזק muchzak in my car. Now, things that
are not real estate but that are chattel, מטלטלין, metaltelin, are things
that often because they change hands, the presumption of who's in possession
of it, in מוחזק muchzak in it, is who's now in possession
of it. Like possession is nine-tenths of the law. Okay, but there
is an idea that when I try now to take you to
court and sue you or you sue me, if I, the one
who is in possession, right? The principle is המוציא מחבירו עליו הראיה.
hamotzi mechavero alav hara'ayah. You're trying to take something away from me,
you have the burden of proof. Okay, and you know, רש"י Rashi
says like בעדים be'edim and so on. So
that's, so therefore in this case, who's מוחזק? muchzak? Well, they're both
physically holding onto it. So they're both equally מוחזק. muchzak. But here,
interestingly, their claims also frame what they're מוחזק muchzak in. So if
I say it's all mine, I'm fully מוחזק. muchzak. You say it's
all yours, you're fully מוחזק. muchzak. So we have a case where
we're both fully מוחזק muchzak in the same object, okay, and therefore
we're a little stuck, right? But let's say, says תוספות, Tosafot, I
say it's half mine and you say it's all yours. So I'm
מוחזק muchzak in half of it. You're מוחזק muchzak in all of
it. Everybody getting this?
So
if I'm going to try to get a מיגו migo to let
me take this full half, I'm using my מיגו, migo, right? Because
if I could have said everything and then we would have split
it, I only said this, at least give me this. But I'm
going to use my מיגו migo to take away your חזקה, chazaka,
because you're also fully מוחזק muchzak in that half. Okay, so anyway,
if people didn't catch the מיגו migo question, don't worry about it.
But the key though is, is that part of what's going on
here is a concept of who is considered to be in possession.
And rather than saying contested possession, nobody's in possession, which is what
you're saying, but that's not what we're saying. We're saying physical possession
which with a claim makes you מוחזק. muchzak. Okay, so one guy
is מוחזק muchzak in all of it. The other guy is מוחזק
muchzak in half of it. Okay, so if you claim all and
I claim all, we're both fully in possession of this object, and
that's partly what forces us to split it, okay, whereas, you know,
again, not to confuse it too much, but let's say Eli there
and I were debating
the status of, this is another case in a different גמרא, Gemara,
of a boat that's out in the port. And I was saying
it's all mine, he was saying it's all his. According to one
גמרא, Gemara, the answer is, you know how what we say there?
Fight it out. Okay, which is so crazy, it's felt like anarchy.
But nevertheless, why? Okay, why? Because neither of us are מוחזק. muchzak.
If there's no מוחזקות, muchzakut, it's like nobody has any claim, you
know, come to us when somebody has some right to it, rather
than just your word. Anarchy. But nevertheless, why? Okay, why? Because neither
of us are מוחזק. muchzak. If there's no מוחזקות, muchzakut, it's like
nobody has any claim. You know, come to us when somebody has
some rights to it rather than just your words, you know? So,
so it is important to understand that a part of what generates
the decision that we've got to split it is because both people
have claims, they're both in possession and and therefore we have to
resolve this. And therefore we split it. Okay?
But does it mean that you're actually physically holding onto it, does
it?
Well, that's the גמרא Gemara will discuss. But no, presumably even if
you're just holding onto an edge of it, you're seen as holding
onto all of it. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara continues, the
משנה Mishnah continues. Okay. היו שנים רוכבין על גבי בהמה, Hayu shenayim
rokhvin al gabi behema, two people were riding on an animal, או
שהיה אחד רוכב ואחד מנהיג, o shehayah echad rokhev ve-echad manhig, or
one was riding and one was leading it. זה אומר כולה שלי
וזה אומר כולה שלי, Zeh omer kullah sheli vezeh omer kullah sheli,
one says it's all mine, the other says it's all mine. Again,
not clear, are they saying they always owned it and the other
guy is just a גנב? ganav? Are they saying they found it
and it was a מציאה? metziah? We'll see in the גמרא Gemara
different scenarios. Anyway, זה ישבע שאין לו בה פחות מחציה וזה ישבע
שאין לו בה פחות מחציה ויחלוקו, Zeh yishava she-ein lo bah pahot
me-hatziyah vezeh yishava she-ein lo bah pahot me-hatziyah ve-yachloku, same הלכה. halakha.
They swear they don't have less than half and they split it.
The חידוש chiddush here though is, and this is going to be
a question, to what extent, well right, what degree of physical possession
is necessary to generate this sense of being מוחזק? muchzak? Okay, so
physically holding into a garment is one thing. Sitting on an animal,
leading an animal, is it related to how you would do a
קנין kinyan on the animal? Is that what it's about? Is it
about physically holding on? That is not explored. But clearly that's part
of the point of this next, it's explored by example, not by
principle. The point of this second example is to say that in
this case as well they're both considered holding onto it.
ובזמן ששניהם מודים, U-vizman she-shneihem modim, if they both agree that they
found it at the same time, או שיש שם עדים, o she-yesh
sham edim, or there's witnesses that say who found it first, or
that witnesses that say, excuse me, that they both own it, חולקין
בלא שבועה, cholkin belo shevuah, then you divide it without a שבועה,
shevuah, which is like a duh, right? If it's all conceded or
there are witnesses, what's the question? So we'll see about that in
the גמרא. Gemara. Okay, but two big חידושים: chiddushim: one is that
you split it; as I said, there are cases where you don't
split it, there are cases where you basically say we're going to
leave it in escrow, we'll see a case like that in the
גמרא, Gemara, or we're going to say you fight it out; but
here the prime reason that you split it is because they're both
in possession of it, they're both מוחזק. muchzak. And the need for
a שבועה, shevuah, the שבועה shevuah number one crafted in a way
that does not lead to a lie and that does not also
undermine your own claim, also in a way that when we in
the end, that is exactly tailored to the end ruling, so that
when we give the ruling in the end, it seems to everybody
that it was a fair and just ruling. Right? Everybody can appreciate
the power of that. You swore, you swore, we divide it exactly
according to that. Okay. But the need for a שבועה shevuah is
because circumstances where even if you're willing to steal you're not willing
to take a false oath, or it's certainly circumstances where you're going
to rationalize to yourself, you will stop rationalizing if you have to
swear to it. Yes, Eli.
Isn't it like aesthetically nicer that they both get half? To the
person who really owned it, I mean, it doesn't...
Yeah, but you can never, you know, you can never do full
justice, right? I mean, we have to do the earthly justice, not
divine justice. What else can we do, right? And we're going to
put the... hook them up to a mind-reading machine? I mean, you
know, it's a good question if they had, if they had, what
do you call them, devices at the time of חז"ל, Chazal, lie
detectors, I don't know what they would have said. But yes?
Just the animal is being split by slaughtering it and...
No, no, no, that's right. Oh, how? So that's what we said.
That's not being explored. It doesn't literally mean you chop it in
half like a Solomon-esque type of a decision, right? You figure out
between the two of them, like, is one of you willing to
sell it to the other? If they both say no,
right, then we... I mean then we would probably sell it and
split the money, right? But that's not being worked out. I still...
I still think that it takes more time for to get on
an animal.
All right, so we'll see about that when we get in the
גמרא, Gemara, why that's considered equal. Okay. למה לי למתני זה אומר
אני מצאתיה וזה אומר אני מצאתיה זה אומר כולה שלי וזה אומר
כולה שלי? Lama li le-matni zeh omer ani metzatiha vezeh omer ani
metzatiha zeh omer kullah sheli vezeh omer kullah sheli? Oh, by the
way, before you continue on, I should just say that תוספות Tosafot
says what is the why why is this פרק perek here? Like
what what's the continuation with the previous מסכת? masekhet? Now again what
you know what you could suggest which I put out there is
is that it's a lead-in to the second פרק perek and we
really want to talk about מציאה, metziah, finding lost objects... again not
to be confused with the word מציאה metziah in בבא מציעא... Bava
Metzia... finding lost objects which is the focus of the second פרק.
perek. So we start here about people arguing about who found the
object and it's a way of exploring that but ultimately it's also
a lead-in to the second פרק. perek. תוספות Tosafot says that it's
also a nice continuation of the last פרק perek in בבא קמא
Bava Kamma because the last פרק perek in בבא קמא Bava Kamma
was I am working for you I'm a carpenter there are some
shavings wood shavings and sawdust and chips of wood who gets to
keep the chips of wood who gets to keep the shavings? So
that's not a question of contesting ownership but it is a question
of dividing things between two people. So not exactly the same but
תוספות Tosafot says maybe that's some degree about how we got to
this you know what the logical transition is to this פרק. perek.
Okay, so let's see the גמרא. Gemara. למה לי למתני זה אומר
אני מצאתיה וזה אומר אני מצאתיה זה אומר כולה שלי וזה אומר
כולה שלי? Lama li le-matni zeh omer ani metzatiha vezeh omer ani
metzatiha zeh omer kullah sheli vezeh omer kullah sheli? Why do you
have to say two cases? I found it, it's scenario number one,
and scenario number two is it's all mine. What
is, what's being added by the second case? ליתני חדא, Litni chada,
just say one case, I found it, I found it. So the
first answer of the גמרא Gemara is חדא קתני, Chada katani, it
is all one case. זה אומר מצאתיה Zeh omer metzatiha וזה אומר
כולה שלי, veze omer kulla sheli, that's what he's saying. I found
it and therefore it's all mine. וזה אומר אני מצאתיה וכולה שלי.
veze omer ani metzatiha vekulla sheli. Okay, וליתני, velisni, so the גמרא
Gemara says fine, even if you say it's one case, we can
still ask why you had to have them say both things. וליתני,
velisni, why not teach, do you have a גמרא? Gemara? Do you
want a גמרא? Gemara? You okay there? All right. Okay, ליתני, lisni,
why don't you say, where was I, וליתני אני
מצאתיה ואנא ידענא דכולה שלי, velisni ani metzatiha ve'ana yadana de-kulla sheli,
just have them say I found it, I found it. Why do
you have to put in their mouth them saying it's all mine?
The claim I found it is a claim that it's all mine.
No, אי תנא אני מצאתיה, i tana ani metzatiha, had you just
said I found it, הוה אמינא מאי מצאתיה ראיתיה, hava amina mai
metzatiha re'itiha, אף על גב דלא אתא לידיה, ראייה בעלמא
קני, af al gav de-lo ata lidei re'iya b'alma kani. because if
you say, hey, I found it first, like anybody in this table,
I found it first does not mean I picked it up first.
It means I saw it first, okay? So therefore, if they just
said I found it first, I found it first, and you said
you split it, you would think that by finding a מציאה, metzia,
spotting the מציאה, metzia, you're entitled to it, okay? And it would,
it would give you a misunderstanding of what entitles you to a
מציאה. metzia. This guy said I found it, I found it, and
they split it, right? If that would be the ruling, you would
think that just spotting the מציאה metzia entitles you to it. So
therefore, we added the phrase 'it's all mine' to indicate it wasn't
enough to just spot it. You had to do something to make
it yours. You had to pick it up. Okay, one minute, let's
get through this. הוה אמינא, hava amina, so the גמרא Gemara
says, אף על גב, af al gav, I would have thought, אף
על גב דלא אתא לידיה af al gav de-lo ata lidei, ראייה
בעלמא קני. re'iya b'alma kani, So therefore, תנא כולה שלי, tana kulla
sheli, it says כולה שלי, kulla sheli, דראייה לא קני, de-re'iya lo
kani, to tell you don't think just spotting it makes it yours.
You had to do something to make it yours. You had to
pick it up. So the גמרא Gemara says, ומי מצית אמרת מאי
מצאתיה ראיתיה, umi mitsat amrit mai metzatiha re'itiha, how would I ever
have thought that I spotted it meant that I found, meant that
I just saw
it? ואמר רבנא, v'amar Ravana, רבנא Ravana set in בבא קמא, Bava
Kamma, just recently, or רבינא Ravina should
be, ומצאתה דאתא לידיה משמע, u'metzatah d'ata lidei mashma, it says if
you find an object, it means that it came into your hand.
The point of that דרשה drasha was in that whole גמרא Gemara
about abrogation to non-Jews and whatever, that you don't have to return
a lost object to a non-Jew unless it's a קידוש השם kiddush
Hashem issue, according to that גמרא. Gemara. So the point was, גמרא
Gemara says well maybe that's only before you picked it up. Maybe
once you picked it up, you do have to give it back
to him. And the גמרא Gemara says no, because it says אשר
תאבד ממנו ומצאתה, asher tavad mimenu u'metzatah,
that your brother loses an object and you find it, and so
it's in the context of your brother, your fellow Jew losing an
object, and you find it, says רבינא Ravina means you picked it
up, okay? And even after you picked it up, you don't have
to return it. So in that context, it says you see ומצאתה
metzatah means you picked it up, not just you saw it. So
I already know that the word to find a lost object means
to pick it up. גמרא Gemara says
אין, in, yes, ומצאתה דקרא דאתא לידיה משמע. u'metzatah de-kra d'ata lidei
mashma. Sure, in the פסוק, pasuk, the דרשה, drasha, we never had
a question that it meant that you actually came in possession. ומיהו
תנא לישנא דעלמא נקט, umihu tana lishan d'alma nakat, our תנא tanna
is talking about how people talk, and what people talk colloquially, I
found it means I spotted it first. This comes up every single
day in New York City about parking spots. What are you going
to say? Taxis! No, that would be another good example. Right, I
saw the spot, but you pulled up to it before me, okay?
So go try to argue that it's really my spot because I
saw it first. One minute, ומדחזי ליה אמר אנא אשכחית, u'mid'chazei lei
amar ana ashkachis, and when somebody sees something, they say I found
it, ואף על גב דלא אתא לידיה, v'af al gav de-lo ata
lidei, and even if they didn't take possession, ראייה בעלמא קני, re'iya
b'alma kani, they would have thought, if it just had said that,
and the משנה Mishnah had recognized 'I found it' as a legitimate
claim, the impression would have been communicated that seeing it gives you
a legitimate claim. Seeing it makes you own. So therefore, תנא כולה
שלי, tana kulla sheli, it says the extra phrase of כולה שלי
kulla sheli to tell you ראייה בעלמא לא קני, re'iya b'alma lo
kani, don't think spotting it is what gives this guy the claim,
it's because he adds to 'I saw it' כולה שלי, kulla sheli,
which means I saw it and I picked it up. Okay, so
רב ספרא Rav Safra and Michael I know has a question, וליתני
כולה שלי ולא בעי אני מצאתיה, velisni kulla sheli v'lo ba'ei ani
metzatiha, so then don't give you the scenario of finding. Just say
this guy says it's all mine, this guy says it's all mine.
Why are we giving the scenario of finding? No, אי תנא כולה
שלי, i tana kulla sheli, if it just had said it's all
mine, it's all mine, הוה אמינא בעלמא דקתני מצאתיה ראייה בעלמא קני,
hava amina b'alma de-katani metzatiha re'iya b'alma kani,
then it wouldn't have told me this point that we're telling me,
it wouldn't have told me what does it mean to find an
object, when are you entitled to an object? Right, it then it
wouldn't have been talking about a lost object at all, you know,
Eli would have been saying it's his, he bought it in the
store and I say I bought it in the store, and we
wouldn't have been talking about that case. So it would have been
okay for this משנה Mishnah's purposes, but it wouldn't have told me
this important point that we've just made, which is spotting an object
doesn't entitle you to it. So we wanted to talk about the
מציאה metzia case, and we wanted to point out that you're only
entitled to the מציאה metzia not just by spotting it, but by
picking it up. Okay,
so
תנא אני מצאתיה, tana ani metzatiha, so
therefore it
says אני מצאתיה, ani metzatiha, והדר תנא כולה שלי, vehadar tana kulla
sheli, דממשנה יתירה אשמעינן דראייה לא קני, de-mi-mishna yeteira ashm'inan de-re'iya lo
kani, that's not enough to spot. It means I found it and
I picked it up and it's all mine. Michael, you've been waiting.
Yeah, so let's say, so I go and invest in a metal
detector and I find like this, a ping, right, on the beach,
and then there's buried treasure and I grab the backhoe and I
start, excavating, but I don't actually touch it, I don't actually pick
it up. And then you go, you've done nothing, and you go
pick up the treasure chest, it's yours?
So according to this, the answer would be yes and it would
be sort of like a type of a, like a גרמא בנזיקין,
grama b'nizikin, it's not a גרמא בנזיקין, grama b'nizikin, but actually there's
a גמרא gemara about עני המהפך בחררה ובא אחר ונטלה. ani hamahapech
b'charara u-ba acher ve-netala. Exactly that case, and which the גמרא gemara
actually has a very heavy moral censure about that, but technically it's
דרכונא. darkona. Okay, so the short answer is yes. Now תוספות Tosafot
does quote a גמרא gemara that says הבטה בהפקר קני. habata b'hefker
kani. Okay, הבטה, habata, הבטה, habata, which sounds like ראייה, re'iya, but
הבטה habata means like peering. And the ראשונים rishonim do have a
discussion of does that really mean that like- now, so say, there's
two answers. One is it doesn't mean הבטה, habata, it means חבטה,
chavata, it means like banging on it, some type of an act
of a קניין, kinyan, okay, but others say that it might mean
a certain type of a not just I spotted it, but a
certain type of like guarding it, watching it, something of that nature.
So it is possible in some according to some ראשונים rishonim that
that might work, that you might technically be קונה, koneh, but more
likely I'd be קונה koneh and I'd be a real like
scoundrel, but I'd be קונה. koneh. Okay. So can you just explain
like that idea, that the law says like prospecting or something, they
claim that area and then somebody...
Well, you can buy rights to the area, but like you mean
oh I found this fishing spot, you have to get out of
it, I found this good spot to prospect for gold in
הפקר hefker land?
Well, then they go back to the
government authority to place their claim.
Oh well then they have rights, and they bought rights to that
space. Yeah. Okay. So before they've gone to the government authority, you
found a spot and I heard you talking to your friend, right,
about oh this great spot and I follow you and then I
start
prospecting, okay. So alright. So the גמרא gemara says like this. Moving
on. All right, the גמרא gemara says like this. והא זה וזה
קתני. ve-ha ze ve-ze katani. All right, but the גמרא gemara says
I don't buy it. I don't buy the משנה's mishna all one
case, because the משנה's mishna phrased as two separate cases. זה אומר
אני מצאתיה וזה אומר אני מצאתיה ze omer ani metzatiha ve-ze omer
ani metzatiha and then it says זה אומר כולו שלי וזה אומר
כולו שלי. ze omer kulo sheli ve-ze omer kulo sheli. It doesn't
sound like you're clarifying the first case, it sounds like you're giving
a second case. If you wanted to say one case with both
phrases, you would have said זה אומר אני מצאתיה וכולו שלי וזה
אומר אני מצאתיה וכולו שלי. ze omer ani metzatiha ve-kulo sheli ve-ze
omer ani metzatiha ve-kulo sheli. By saying זה אומר וזה אומר, זה
אומר וזה אומר, ze omer ve-ze omer, ze omer ve-ze omer, it
sounds like there are two cases here. So we have to come
up with another answer. So אמר רב פפא ואיתימא רב שימי בר
אשי ואמרי לה כדי, amar Rav Pappa ve-itayma Rav Shimi bar Ashi
ve-amri lah kadi, some say כדי, kadi,
which basically means no one, okay, or which means like or was
said anonymously, okay, רישא במציאה וסיפא במקח וממכר. reisha bi-metzia ve-seifa be-mekach
u-memkar.
It is two cases: the first case is we're fighting over who
found the object, meaning who picked it up first, and the second
case is who bought the object. Now, by the way, you realize
that it could have been a question of not just who bought
the object, but like who owned it? Like what are you talking
about, I bought this ten, I
mean like I inherited this from my
father, right, so there's that so I'll talk about that case in
a minute, but let's deal with the גמרא's gemara scenario. Okay.
Does he mean anything by מציאה metzia then?
Right, I mean everything we said is true להלכה, le-halacha, but it's
not what the משנה's mishna talking about. Okay. So we're talking about
two cases. One is who found it and the other is who
bought it, וצריכא, u-tzricha, you need both cases. And now what we
pretty much already understand what the מציאה metzia case is, let's understand
what the מקח וממכר mekach u-memkar case is. אי תנא מציאה, Ee
tana metzia, had it just been a debate, now on the עמוד
ב amud bet about who found the object, הוה אמינא מציאה הוא
דרמו רבנן שבועה עליה משום דמורי ואמר. hava amina metzia hu de-ramu
rabbanan shevua lei mishum de-mori ve-amar. Now this the גמרא gemara right
now is doing a classic thing the גמרא gemara does, although often
it's more technical, here it gets to the meat right away. Often
at the beginning of a מסכת, masechet, the גמרא gemara focuses on
some side issue of some language issue, but in the course of
dealing with some language issue it brings in some of the themes.
Here it really does get right away to the meat of it.
But because it's not just a language issue, it's like what are
the two cases in the משנה? mishna? But what it's doing right
at the beginning is introducing some of the major themes. And it's
going to say why you might need to tell me both the
case of a lost object and the case of fighting over who
bought it is because there might be a reason in one case
that you think a שבועה shevua would be effective rather than another.
And by immediately pointing out why there might be a better reason
in one than the other, we're immediately getting to the root of
what is the function of the שבועה shevua and how does it
work. You understand? Right, because by saying oh it makes more sense
here than here, that forces us to say why does it make
sense? What is it about? And the גמרא gemara right away says
and the key word here is מורי ואמר. mori ve-amar. Okay, מורי
ואמר mori ve-amar means you know you're מורה היתר. moreh heter. מורה
moreh is הוראה, hora'ah, right, you give a פסק, psak, but when
you're מורה היתר, moreh heter, you're מורה היתר לעצמו. moreh heter le-atzmo.
You give... Basically give yourself a פסק. psak. Okay, we're doing this
all the time. That's what rationalizing is. Yeah, it's totally fine for
me to take some of the, you know, the pens from the
supply cabinet, I work here anyway, right? You know? So everybody is,
that's the biggest problem that we're מורה היתר moreh heter to ourselves.
Okay? So that's why you go to somebody else to get a
פסק psak and you don't פוסקן pasken for yourself. So here the
גמרא Gemara is saying that that's the function of the שבועה shvua
to stop you from rationalizing. All right, and there's a, there could
be a different argument why you'd be more likely to rationalize even
if it's not yours but you're claiming it's yours in the case
of מציאה metzia and another argument to say why there's more reason
to rationalize in the case of buying an object. Yes, אליהו, Eliyahu,
you had a question? No, I answered it myself. Okay. So let's
see what the answers are. Yes.
That could be a good connection to the previous, the end of
the previous מסכת, masechet, right? Because that was all about are you
going to rationalize with this stuff?
Oh, about like keeping the little, the little pieces of the wood
or whatever. Oh, that's interesting. Nice. Okay. אי תנא מציאה, ei tani
metzia, had we just had the case of a lost object, הוה
אמינא, hava amina, I would have thought, מציאה הוא דרמו רבנן שבועה
עליה, metzia hu de-ramu rabanan shvua alei, מציאה metzia is where the
Rabbis put a שבועה, shvua, they thought it was necessary and would
be effective, משום דמורי ואמר, mishum de-mori ve-amar, because you rationalize and
you say, חבראי לאו מידי חסר בה, chaverai lav midi chasar bah,
look, yes, it's true what Eli saw it first, but you know
what, a minute ago he didn't have it, it was just סתם
stam good luck, he's not really losing out on anything that a
minute ago he, you know, he wanted or he was looking for
before. And you know, I'm a better person than him. I should
be, I should get it, why should he get it? Okay? I
should have it, so I'll just grab it, it falls by then,
and I'll take half of it and I'll get it. Okay? Because
he's not really losing out on anything he had before, he didn't
even want it, it was just סתם stam it came his way.
So I've rationalized to myself why that's okay. אבל מקח וממכר, aval
mekach u-memkar, but let's say we're both arguing over who bought this
mule. We both went to the market, we both needed a mule,
and he's saying he bought it and I'm saying I bought it.
Now the גמרא's Gemara going to say that, that it's, we both
gave the merchant money and the merchant doesn't remember who bought it
first and whatever, we were just throwing money at him. So whoever's
going to lose the case is going to get his money back.
Okay? So I'm not stealing any money from Eli if I say
it's my mule and he bought it because then the merchant will
just give him his money back rather than give me my money
back. But nevertheless, it's going to be, we'll get to that. Nevertheless,
it's harder for me to rationalize. He went to the market knowing
he needed a mule, he spotted the mule, he bought it, you
know, he clear, and I'm going to now grab it from him?
Like what type of a person am I, right? That was something
that he went out to get and I'm taking it away from
him. Right, he invested...
He invested
time, he clearly wanted it, he clearly needed it, right? So it's
harder for me to rationalize why it's סתם stam okay for me
to just grab. Okay? So, so אבל מקח וממכר דליכא למימר הכי,
aval mekach u-memkar de-leika le-meimar hachi, you can't say that, maybe a
שבועה shvua wouldn't work. If I'm going to say in that case
that it's mine, even though it's hard, it's less basis to rationalize,
a שבועה shvua won't work. Why won't a שבועה shvua work? Because
if I can't rationalize, one or two things are true. Okay? Either,
what's the one or two possibilities? If I can't rationalize why it's
okay for me to take it knowing it's not mine? So if
I'm not rationalizing, what am I doing? Stealing. Stealing, or there's another
possibility. Or he's mistaken? Believing I'm telling the truth. Okay? So there's
two possible scenarios in a case where I can't rationalize. Either it's
like what do I care that it's his, I'm a גנב ganav
and I don't care, what's yours is mine and I'm going to
steal it. Okay? If that's the type of person I am, a
שבועה shvua most likely won't work, or that's a question, will a
שבועה shvua work on somebody who knows they're a גנב? ganav? Okay,
but the other possibility is if I can't rationalize and I'm still
claiming it's mine, it must mean because I really believe it's mine.
If I really believe it's mine, a שבועה shvua isn't going to
do any good either. So a שבועה shvua most works in a
case where I'm rationalizing. Okay? So in the case of מקח וממכר
mekach u-memkar where I can't rationalize, in that case אימא לא, eima
lo, maybe there won't be a שבועה, shvua, what would be the
point of a שבועה? shvua? אי תנא מקח וממכר, ei tani mekach
u-memkar, you'd have to
make a שבועה shvua also.
But you do. And now we're going to say why there, in
the flip. So just tell me the case of מקח וממכר mekach
u-memkar there's a שבועה, shvua, no, there's an argument to be made
that it's מקח וממכר mekach u-memkar that there's more of a rationalizing
going on. Let's hear this. אי תנא מקח וממכר הוא דרמו רבנן
שבועה עליה, ei tani mekach u-memkar hu de-ramu rabanan shvua alei,
I would say that's the case where a שבועה shvua works, it's
the מקח וממכר mekach u-memkar that there's more of a rationalizing going
on. Why? משום דמורי ואמר, mishum de-mori ve-amar, here's how you rationalize
why I can grab Eli's mule from him. דמיא קיהיב ואנא דמיא
קיהיב, demeika yahiv ve-ana demeika yahiv, look, I'm paying for it, I
gave the money to the merchant as well, he's going to get
his money back, so at the end of the day is he
going to be out any money? No. השתא דצריכא לדידי, hashta de-tzricha
lidi, and I need the mule more than him, I know it,
he's got plenty of mules, I'm more in need of it, אשקלי
אנא, ashkelei ana, I'll take it, וחבראי ליזיל ליטרח וליזבן, ve-chaverai leizel
litrach ve-lizban, he'll get his money back, he'll find another one, he's
got more time on his hands anyway, it's totally okay. Okay? So
I've rationalized that whole thing. But אבל מציאה... aval metzia... You see
how good I am at rationalizing?
I've had a lot of practice. Okay. So...
Exactly. אבל מציאה דליכא למימר הכי aval metziah deleika leimeir hachi now,
but if he found a wallet, or he found a lost mule
wandering around, I can't rationalize it because if I take it from
him, he's not getting that mule back. He just got a free
mule, and if I take it away from him, he's out the
value of that lost object. In the case where he bought it,
he'll get his money back, he'll buy another one, it's just effort.
But here, if I claim a lost object that he found and
I claim it's mine, then I'm really taking away an object from
him that he's not going to get back. So maybe it's harder
for me to rationalize that case. Okay, אבל מציאה aval metziah so...
אבל מציאה דליכא למימר הכי, aval metziah deleika leimeir hachi, אימא לא,
eima lo, maybe in that case where I can't rationalize, either I
know I'm lying or I totally believe I'm telling the truth, one
or the other, a שבועה shvuah might not work. צריכה, tzricha, you
need to tell me both cases. Okay, so that was a great
little piece of גמרא. Gemara. It was great מוסר mussar for ראש
השנה Rosh Hashanah about how good we are at rationalizing. But it
was also great at getting to the point about how the point
of a שבועה, shvuah, the most effective use of the שבועה shvuah
is when somebody is rationalizing, because the שבועה shvuah gets them to
like look in the mirror and, you know, be more honest with
themselves. It really is like a ראש השנה יום הדין Rosh Hashanah
Yom HaDin type of a thing. Okay, so that's how it's most
effective. But if you think you're telling the truth, it won't work.
And if you know that and if you know you're lying, that's
debatable whether it'll work. Okay, but the best effectiveness of it is
the rationalizing and it tells us why there's the שבועה shvuah in
the משנה, Mishnah, what the שבועה shvuah is coming to do. Now
the גמרא Gemara is going to step back and ask about... why
is this that we don't have any other evidence to bring to
bear on these cases? Okay, so let's take a look. מקח וממכר,
Mekach Umemkar, now you're telling me that case number two is one
about buying an object from a merchant and not knowing who bought
it. So the גמרא Gemara says, I told you before that both
of them threw money at the merchant, but we don't know that
yet. ולחזי זוזי ממי נקט? velechzei zuzei mimi nakat? Why not just
see who paid for it? Now the question is, who are we
believing who paid for it? Maybe they're arguing who paid for it.
So, you know, so תוספות Tosafot says well like, you know, no,
like let's at least ask them, maybe they'll admit, maybe I'll say
sure Eli paid for it but he agreed to sell it to
me. Like maybe I'm not going to lie you know saying that
I'm robbing the money from you by claiming I paid for it
when I didn't, maybe whatever. So maybe maybe they'll admit who paid
for it and then we could just use that. That's one way
of understanding. Another way of understanding it is maybe we'll believe the
merchant who paid for it. The merchant will say. And that gets
into a whole interesting question of whether the guy who's selling it
has special believability, I don't know if that's even a word, anyway
has special weight to his claim more than a normal person. I'm
selling it, I'm paying attention, you should believe me, I know who
paid for it. Okay, the third thing that תוספות Tosafot says is
even if I the seller don't have any special weight to my
claim, I'm at least an עד אחד. eid echad. Okay, so here
actually I'll be since I was since I was one of the
litigants, I won't be the merchant, Michael will be the merchant. So
Michael comes and says yeah Eli paid for it. Okay, so he's
not two עדים, eidim, but what is he? He's an עד אחד.
eid echad. So an עד אחד eid echad first of all exempts
Eli from having to make a שבועה. shvuah. If an עד אחד
eid echad backs up your claim, right, so he frees Eli from
having to make a שבועה shvuah and he makes me have to
make a שבועה דאורייתא. shvuah de'oraita. This is a דרבנן שבועה. derabbanan
shvuah. But to respond to the claim of an עד אחד eid
echad you have to take a biblical שבועה shvuah which is more
weighty. So תוספות Tosafot says, you know, even if it wouldn't totally
solve the case, it would be a very relevant fact that that
the merchant is claiming who, you know, who paid for it. So
let's just ask and find out who paid for it and we'll
assume the person who paid for it, now you realize הלכתית halachically
paying for it doesn't make you own it, right? After you pay
for it you have to actually pick it up, but there's a
presumption here that if you paid for it, you're the one the
merchant wanted to sell it to. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this,
ולחזי זוזי ממי נקט, velechzei zuzei mimi nakat, let's just see who
who he took the money from. צריכה, tzricha, we need it for
the case דנקט מתרווייהו. denakat mitarveihu. He took money from both of
them. Not like he's going to steal. מחד מדעתו ומחד בעל כרחו.
michad mida'ato umichad ba'al karcho. One he agreed to take the money,
the other forced him to take the money. ולא ידעינן velo yadainan
or some of the גרסאות girsa'ot ולא ידעי, velo yadei, we don't
know, he doesn't know, מיהו מדעתו מיהו בעל כרחו. mihu mida'ato mihu
ba'al karcho. Who did it willingly? Who he forced? They both threw
money at me, I remember I agreed to sell it to one
of them, they were fighting, I can't remember which one. Okay, that's
the case. Okay, so fine. So now we have understood that we're
talking about a מציאה metziah and about a case of purchase where
by where both paid money. So we don't have any extra evidence
because both paid money. Also nobody is actually losing out dollars and
cents if we award it to one rather than the other because
the other guy will get his money back. And that leads to
cases where there's ways to rationalize both the מציאה metziah case and
rationalize the מקח וממכר mekach umemkar case. Now before we go on
I should say what about a case where there cannot be an
honest mistake or debate about who said what? I believe I saw,
you believe you saw. Let's... Okay there's no question that one of
us is an out and out liar. You basically say, this is
the mule that has been in my family for the last ten
years, and you say, this is the mule that has been in
my family for the last ten years. Okay, there's no question that
one of us is out and out lying. The way רשי Rashi
gives the example is, if we're fighting about a garment, let's say
I say, I wove this garment, and you say, no, I wove
this garment. There is no question that one of us is lying,
right? So in that case, what would you say? So first of
all, תוספות Tosafot says it seems pretty clear from the גמרא Gemara
that you would not take a שבועה, shvua, right? What's the point
of taking a שבועה shvua if somebody is brazenly lying? Unless you
say חשוד אממונא לא חשוד אשבועתא. chashuda amamona lo chashuda ashvuasa. Okay,
that's going to be... well, I'll tell you in a minute. But
first question, there's two questions here. Thank you. Do you take a
שבועה shvua and what do you do with the object? So the
first question is, would a שבועה shvua be any good? So that's
going to be the question of: does a שבועה shvua help for
somebody that knows that they're a גנב, gannav, that's not rationalizing? That's
question number one. Thank you very much. Question number two, though, is:
would you split it? Okay? And there you could say that if
we know somebody is lying, we בית דין Bet Din are not
going to render a judgment that we know cannot be true. Like,
that if splitting it we know that gets to your question before
whatever, like maybe or your question, maybe that's not the reality, but
maybe it is and we have to make a choice. But if
we know it's impossible that you own half and you own half—you're
saying you wove it, you say you wove it—it's all one or
all the other. Are we still going to split it and just
say it's essentially like not true justice but the best we could
do? Is that something that a בית דין Bet Din could allow
themselves to do? Or would a בית דין Bet Din have to
say in that case, you know, we're going to hold it in
escrow, or go fight it out, or something other than splitting it?
Okay.
Till עד שיבוא אליהו, ad sheyavo
Eliyahu, till more evidence comes to light.
Okay. What's my downside of claiming anything? Because I can say, you
know, like...
Right, well that's the thing, you could always use that as a
way, right, how people could sort of manipulate the system we'll get
to. But right now I just want to put out on the
table that רשי Rashi says when one of us is definitely lying,
רשי Rashi says מונח עד שיבוא אליהו, munach ad sheyavo Eliyahu, which
is something we're going to see tomorrow. Hold it in escrow until
some more evidence comes to light. We cannot participate in that. You
know, it's possible, though, you could say we will split it, we
just won't make a שבועה. shvua. Alright, so that's a really interesting
question about, you know, בית דין Bet Din is supposed to be
דין, din, not פשרה. peshara. But, you know, it's like we don't
know, we'll never know all the facts. We have to do the
best with the facts and evidence. Can we give a ruling which
might be the fairest we could do but certainly not the right
and certainly not, you know, true justice? Will we allow ourselves to
give that type of a ruling? Okay, so anyway, so something really
to think about. Let's take a look now as the גמרא Gemara
continues. So גמרא Gemara says like this: לימא, Leima, now we're going
to focus on a series of other Tannaic statements that speak about
dividing objects and the focus is going to be not on the
fact that we divide the object, again that's sort of we're taking
for granted, but on whether or not we make a שבועה. shvua.
Is it really true that everybody agreed you would make a שבועה
shvua in a case like this? So let's take a look.
לימא מתניתין דלא כבן ננס. Leima matnitan d'lo ke-Ben Nanas. Let's say
our משנה Mishna is not like בן ננס. Ben Nanas. דאי בן
ננס, Di-ei Ben Nanas, if it's בן ננס, Ben Nanas, הא אמר
בן ננס ha amar Ben Nanas says, כיצד אלו ואלו באין לידי
שבועת שוא? keitzad elu v'elu ba'in lidei shvuat shav? How can we
let this one and that one come to a false oath? Or
at least one of them come to a false oath. Now he
doesn't say it about our case, okay, he says it about the
following case. I say to Michael, Michael, you own a מכולת makolet
there in Israel. My son's in Israel this year. When he comes,
just give him everything on credit, tell me how much he took
and I'll pay you for it. Okay? Or I tell my work,
give my workers, you know, feed them. You own a restaurant, maybe
we make a better case. Not my son, feed, you own a
restaurant, it's, you know, give them when they come in, just feed
them, tell me what the bill is, I'll pay it. Okay? So
then at the end of the day, Michael says, okay, a hundred
dollars, that's what they spent. My workers come in and say, we
went to Michael, he refused to feed us, you know, and you
promised that you would give us a lunch. Okay? So what do
I do? Okay, do I give Michael a hundred dollars? Do I
give my workers? Do I give neither of them? So the first
ruling is Michael swears that he set that he gave them the
food and it cost a, you know, for a hundred dollars. They
swear they didn't get the food from Michael, and I pay both
of them. Okay? So in that case בן ננס Ben Nanas says,
one of them is definitely lying! How do we allow a שבועת
שוא shvuat shav to definitely take place? Okay, so according to בן
ננס, Ben Nanas, maybe we don't let both sides take a שבועה.
shvua. Now the answer is obvious, the difference is obvious, but it
allows the גמרא Gemara to say it explicitly. So the גמרא Gemara
says no. התם ודאי איכא שבועת שוא. Hatam vadai ika shvuat shav.
There definitely one of them is taking a false oath. It's interesting
calls it שבועת שוא shvuat shav and not שבועת שקר. shvuat sheker.
Anyway, הכא איכא למימר דליכא שבועת שוא. hacha ika leimeir d'leka shvuat
shav.
Who says that there's a false oath? אימא דתרווייהו בהדי הדדי אגבהוה.
Eima d'tarveihu bahadi hadadi agbeu. Now maybe a minute ago we didn't
think of the likelihood they both picked it up at the same
time, you know, what's the chances of that? Right, even if you're
just swearing half, we assumed one of you is still lying. But
now the גמרא Gemara is saying no, there really is a possible
scenario that they both own half of it. They both picked it
up at the same time, that the merchant agreed to sell it
to both of them, he couldn't get into their fight. Fine.
But actually is tailored in a way that it's possible that each
one is taking an honest שבועה, Shvua, unlikely but possible. And that's
why this can work even according to בן ננס. Ben Nanas. Okay,
so that's point number one. The שבועה Shvua is not necessarily שבועת
שוא, Shvuat Shav, which means if it definitely is a שבועת שוא,
Shvuat Shav, like the case I said before, I wove it, you
say you wove it, right? Maybe we wouldn't take the שבועה. Shvua.
All right. Okay, that's number and not only because it's a שבועת
שוא, Shvuat Shav, also because a שבועה Shvua wouldn't force me to
admit because I'm knowingly lying. All right, but in this case, I'm
not knowingly lying and it's possible it's a שבועת אמת, Shvuat Emet,
and therefore we can do it. Next case says the גמרא. Gemara.
לימא מתניתין דלא כסומכוס. Leima Matnitin Dlo KeSumchus.
Let's say our משנה Mishna is not like סומכוס. Sumchus. סומכוס, Sumchus,
you might remember, we heard about him a lot in בבא קמא.
Bava Kamma. He said, I basically, I sold my cow to Eli
there, and he went to pick it up and it had been
pregnant and there was a baby calf by it. And Eli says
the sale went through before the baby calf was born and it's
my baby calf, and I say the sale went through after the
baby calf was born and it's my baby calf. And so the
חכמים Chachamim say, like המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה, Hamotzi Mechaveiro Alav Haraya,
since I was the default owner before, I'm considered the owner until
Eli can prove that it was his. סומכוס Sumchus says, ממון המוטל
בספק חולקין. Mamon Hamutal Besafek Cholkin. No, there's a doubt, there's no
way of knowing, we split it, okay, even though I was the
default owner. So the גמרא Gemara says like this, לימא מתניתין דלא
כסומכוס, Leima Matnitin Dlo KeSumchus, let's say our משנה Mishna is not
like סומכוס. Sumchus. דאי כסומכוס, De'ee KeSumchus, if it's like סומכוס, Sumchus,
הא אמר סומכוס, Ha Amar Sumchus, סומכוס Sumchus says ממון המוטל בספק
חולקין, Mamon Hamutal Besafek Cholkin,
whenever there's a doubt, whenever there's a you know some type of
a serious doubt about who owns the thing, you split it. בלא
שבועה, Belo Shvua, adds the גמרא. Gemara.
סומכוס Sumchus never demands a שבועה. Shvua. So yes, it's חולקין, Cholkin,
and our משנה Mishna is חולקין, Cholkin, but סומכוס Sumchus never demands
a שבועה, Shvua, so let's say our משנה Mishna is not like
סומכוס. Sumchus.
So גמרא Gemara says ואלא מאי, Ve'ella Mai, so what do you
want to say? רבנן? Rabbanan? It's the rabbis who argue on סומכוס?
Sumchus? האמרי, Ha Amri, but the רבנן Rabbanan say not only do
you not make a שבועה, Shvua, they say you don't even split
it. המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi Mechaveiro Alav Haraya. They say, you
know, you need real proof, you need witnesses. So forget שבועה, Shvua,
why would you split it according to the רבנן? Rabbanan? So גמרא
Gemara says האי מאי, Hai Mai, what type of question is that?
אי אמרת בשלמא רבנן, Ee Amrat Bishlama Rabbanan, if you say that
it's the רבנן Rabbanan it makes sense. Why? התם דלא תפסי תרוייהו,
Hatam Dlo Tafsi Tarvayu, in that case we're not both we don't
have equal claims, this cow was originally mine. I'm the מוחזק, Muchzak,
I'm the default owner. So in that case there is a מוציא,
Motzi, Eli's coming to take it out of my possession.
Okay, אמרו רבנן המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Amru Rabbanan Hamotzi Mechaveiro Alav
Haraya. Eli, you want to say that calf is yours? You go
prove it. I'm the default owner. Okay, so that's why they say
no שבועה, Shvua, no split, because there's a default owner. הכא דתרוייהו
תפסי, Hacha Detarvayu Tafsi, here that they both are have claims and
they're both holding on, פלגי לה בשבועה. Palgi Lah Bishvua. A, they'll
say split, and B, they'll say if we're splitting but we don't
have any you know but a שבועה Shvua could be helpful to
getting to the bottom of it, we'll be splitting plus a שבועה.
Shvua. Okay, so the רבנן Rabbanan make sense. If a guy is
מוחזק, Muchzak, המוציא מחברו עליו הראיה. Hamotzi Mechaveiro Alav Haraya. Two people
are equally מוחזק, Muchzak, split it with a שבועה. Shvua. The שבועה
Shvua might help out. Okay, but סומכוס Sumchus doesn't make sense.
Okay, אלא אי
אמרת סומכוס, Ella Ee Amrat Sumchus, but if you
say סומכוס, Sumchus, השתא התם דלא תפסי תרוייהו, Hashta Hatam Dlo Tafsi
Tarvayu, if in the case by the cow and the calf where
not both holding on, I have more of a presumption of ownership,
and nevertheless חולקין בלא שבועה, Cholkin Belo Shvua, we're going to split
it without a שבועה, Shvua, so we're really it's a big חידוש,
Chidush, we're taking it away from my חזקה Chazaka and splitting it
and we don't even ask for a שבועה Shvua in that case
even though it's getting taken out of my hands. So הכא דתרוייהו
תפסי לה, Hacha Detarvayu Tafsi Lah, here where they both have an
equal claim, the idea of splitting is more obvious and certainly כל
שכן Kol Sheken that you shouldn't need a שבועה, Shvua, right? If
סומכוס Sumchus says you don't need a שבועה Shvua when Eli is
taking it out of my hands, why should he need a שבועה
Shvua when we're both equally claimed to it? Great question. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, אפילו תימא סומכוס, Afilu Teima Sumchus, סומכוס Sumchus
could still agree to our משנה. Mishna. כי אמר סומכוס שמא ושמא,
Ki Amar Sumchus Shema Vashema, when does סומכוס Sumchus say that you
don't make a שבועה? Shvua? Like the calf, when both of us
say I don't know for sure when the calf was born, I'm
just I just think that, I'd like to believe it was born
when I owned it, but none of us know. Since none of
us know, what type of שבועה Shvua are we supposed to make?
I take a שבועה Shvua that I believe the calf was born
while I still owned it, right? Of course, that's crazy. So in
his case where they don't know, there's no purpose to a שבועה.
Shvua. אבל ברי וברי, Aval Bari Vavari, in this case where each
one is making a definite claim, לא אמר, Lo Amar, he would
not say don't do a שבועה, Shvua, meaning he would admit here,
even though each one has more rights, here since they're making a
definite claim, a שבועה Shvua can be effective, right? They can make
a שבועה Shvua to their definite claim and they can back off
if they're forced to make a שבועה. Shvua. I said everybody get
it?
The question, is there more of a reason as to rationalizing?
No, not because of more of a reason to rationalize, but because
you can't make a שבועה shevuah about a שמא, shema, right? I
mean first of all what would the שבועה shevuah even be? And
number two is right, because if you're making a ברי bari claim
and you have to make a שבועה shevuah about it you might
drop your ברי bari claim.
What about a חזקה דהשתא chazakah dehashta versus a ברי ושמא?
bari veshema? Oh, can we please not go there? Okay, so anyway,
the גמרא's Gemara basic point is that why do you make a
שבועה? shevuah? Yes, there's an idea that you would never העז פניו,
he'ez panav, you would never make a definite שבועת שוא, shvuat shav,
but it's not a שבועת שוא shvuat shav here. Number two, there's
an idea of סומכוס Sumchus don't make a שבועה, shevuah, but the
גמרא's Gemara answer is but maybe that's only when there's everybody's a
שמא, shema, so there's no שבועה shevuah to be made. Okay,
one minute, fine.
Okay, so fine, but if it's a ברי, bari, maybe he would
agree. But now we have a question because some people say that
סומכוס Sumchus doesn't require שבועה shevuah even in the case of ברי.
bari. So the גמרא Gemara says like this: ורבה בר רב הונא
דאמר אמר סומכוס אפילו ברי וברי, u'le'Rabba bar Rav Huna de'amar amar
Sumchus afilu bari u'bari, one minute, רבה בר רב הונא Rabba bar
Rav Huna says סומכוס Sumchus would say split without a שבועה shevuah
even if you're taking away from a חזקה chazakah and even if
each one is making a ברי. bari. I say I saw when
it was giving birth, and I saw it gave birth after. He
says no I saw and I saw before. We're each making a
ברי. bari. And סומכוס Sumchus still says split without a שבועה. shevuah.
So if I can take it out of my חזקה chazakah and
he can get half without a שבועה, shevuah, then why wouldn't... then
certainly when we're both holding onto the טלית tallis he should get
half without a שבועה? shevuah? So presumably סומכוס Sumchus would not be
our משנה. mishnah. So the גמרא Gemara says: No, אפילו תימא סומכוס,
afilu teima Sumchus,
even if סומכוס Sumchus says ברי וברי, bari u'bari, it's not the
same as our משנה. mishnah. כי אמר
סומכוס, ki amar Sumchus, when does סומכוס Sumchus say split without a
שבועה? shevuah? היכא דאיכא דררא דממונא. heicha de'ika drara demamona. אבל היכא
דליכא דררא דממונא לא. aval heicha delika drara demamona lo. Now this
word דררא דממונא, drara demamona, it's a big מחלוקת ראשונים machlokes Rishonim
what it means, but I'm going to bracket רש"י. Rashi. רש"י Rashi
says it means הפסד hefsed of money. Almost all the ראשונים Rishonim
say it means an objective stake, an objective claim. Now, what does
that mean? You might say that our case of holding the טלית
tallis is a דררא דממונא. drara demamona. You have a claim because
you're holding it on. But תוספות Tosafos clarifies it a little bit
more, which means
דררא דממונא drara demamona means it's not that your stake is generated
just by what you say to בית דין. beis din. Even if
בית דין beis din would come and look at the facts, just
look at the evidence that is known, that is accepted, they would
realize there's an objective ספק. safek. They know that I sold you
the cow, we know that the calf was born, there's an obvious
objective question of when was the calf born. That sort of objective
ספק safek gives more mandate splitting it and splitting it without a
שבועה. shevuah. Here where the whole issue is generated because you're grabbing
and making a claim and it's not somehow some question of just
objective facts generating a question of what happened, right?
So that's the case where it's all a function of your claim
and your actions. So that's where we say, let's make a שבועה
shevuah to get to the bottom of it. All right, is that
sort of clear?
In one
case the שבועה shevuah is as a way of pushing your claim
and getting you to be more honest about your claim. But if
the question arises even without the claim just because of the nature
of the facts, then it's less of a reason to make a
שבועה. shevuah.
But isn't this the nature of the facts?
Well yeah, it's always the facts, who picked it up first or
whatever. Right. But the point is this is a fact that's generated
because of... it's hard to exactly articulate. I understand what you're grappling
with. It's the fact is I'm holding onto it. Why am I
holding onto it? But the fact only somehow means something because of
your claim that's backing it. Whereas even if you didn't claim anything
to בית דין, beis din, you just say, here's what happened. Here's
the stuff we can all agree upon. Maybe that's a good way
of starting it. What would be the things you could all agree
on? We all agreed that דב Dov sold me his donkey and
דב Dov sold me his cow and that the cow gave birth
at some time and we just don't know when. Okay? So if
that's what we can all agree upon, then that's a דררא דממונא.
drara demamona. Don't we all agree that both persons
put money, we both see money?
Maybe in the merchant's case I hear that a little bit more,
but in the מציאה metziah case what do we both agree on?
We don't both agree on anything. All we agree on is that
we're both holding onto a טלית, tallis, right? There's very little that
we actually agree on. Okay that, oh you're both holding onto a
טלית, tallis, so what? So what are the circumstances? What are the
claims? What are the issues? Okay so that's basically the way תוספות
Tosafos says it, although I do understand Eli's question, exactly what's considered
to be generating the ספק. safek. But you take what's agreed upon
and if there's still an objective question, that's דררא דממונא, drara demamona,
therefore split it without a שבועה. shevuah. If the whole thing is
sort of generated by the claims, then we want a שבועה shevuah
to get somebody to admit. Okay so that's basically the answer, the
גמרא's Gemara answer. Let's just read one more line. גמרא Gemara says
like this: אפילו תימא סומכוס, כי אמר סומכוס היכא דאיכא דררא דממונא.
afilu teima Sumchus, ki amar Sumchus heicha de'ika drara demamona. That's when
you split it without a שבועה. shevuah. אבל היכא דליכא דררא דממונא
לא. aval heicha delika drara demamona lo. And now the גמרא Gemara
pushes back: ולאו קל וחומר הוא? ve'lav kal vachomer hu?
One minute, it's a קל וחומר! kal vachomer! Why is it a
קל וחומר kal vachomer to say that you should not make a
שבועה shevuah in this case? Why? Because מה... mah... It's true by
the case of the calf, each one has an objective reason why
it could be theirs, but here's the real point: the איכא למימר
כולו למר ואיכא למימר כולו למר. Ika L'meimar Kulo Lemar V'ika L'meimar
Kulo Lemar. In the case of the calf, it's either all your
calf or all my calf, and in that case אמר שמואל ממון
המוטל בספק חולקין בלא שבועה, Amar Shmuel Mamon Hamutal Besafek Cholkin Belo
Shevua, and we split it, so this is going to be a
little less about the שבועה Shevua and more about the splitting. In
סומכוס's Sumchus case, we're going to split it even though we know
the calf is not half-owned by each of us. We know the
calf is all mine or all yours, we're going to be willing
to split it, which is a judgment that is really not כפי
האמת, K'fi Ha'emet, it's a type of a פשרה, Pshara, and we're
going to be willing to do it without even trying to use
a שבועה Shevua to help us get more to the bottom of
it. So we're going to do a פסק, Psak, which we know
is false, without a שבועה. Shevua. So he says, if in סומכוס's
Sumchus case you're willing to split it even though it's clearly not
כפי האמת K'fi Ha'emet and you're going to do that even without
a שבועה, Shevua, so in that case, הכא דליכא דררא דממונא, Hacha
D'leka Drara D'mamona, here there's not an objective ספק, Safek, which really
means, I mean the דררא דממונא Drara D'mamona here is like a
at this point a red herring, the real point is the איכא
למימר דתרווייהו, Ika L'meimar D'travaihu, here where it genuinely could be both
of theirs, so your פסק Psak of splitting it is a more
legitimate פסק. Psak. So if it's a more legitimate פסק, Psak, there
should be less of a need to make a שבועה. Shevua. כל
שכן, Kol Shekein, you certainly shouldn't make a שבועה. Shevua. Okay, so
therefore, so what the גמרא Gemara is saying is, if you're willing
to not ask for a שבועה Shevua when your פסק Psak is
clearly not כפי האמת, K'fi Ha'emet, you should also not be asking
for a שבועה Shevua when your פסק Psak might be כפי האמת.
K'fi Ha'emet. Now, I don't know that's such a big question, because
bottom line here, the problem is still generated by your claims, and
a שבועה Shevua can help us get to the bottom of those
claims and if those claims are true. But that's the גמרא's Gemara
question. We don't understand why if סומכוס Sumchus doesn't require a שבועה
Shevua there, he should require a שבועה Shevua here. Here the פסק
Psak of יחלוקו Yachloku is a better פסק. Psak. So I'm not
going to give you the answer, we're going to come tomorrow to
the answer about why סומכוס Sumchus might still agree that you make
a שבועה Shevua here and not over there. So to be continued
tomorrow.